[Music]
welcome to the latest rebel wisdom
podcast I'm really excited about this
one because it's some of the best
interviews that we've done recently that
we're making live at the same time as
we're releasing this I'm going to show
some clips from them and there is a
theme and the theme is masculinity and I
guess the sub theme is it's what about a
year now since me too and since a lot of
these gender dynamics started becoming
really prevalent and really part of the
culture and that's been a big theme of a
lot of the stuff that we've been doing
so what we've got coming up at the same
time is two interviews and another round
of content probably bout a week after
that so we have an interview with Cassie
J who directed the red pill film and
we've got into Warren Farrell who is
often called the father of the men's
movement but I think our experience when
we met him in America and interviewed
him is that he's got a lot more to offer
than that sort of characterization he's
a therapist he does couples counseling
he's deeply interested in how to create
healthy relationships and this
ultimately I think is the theme of a lot
of the content we're putting out is what
if if what we're seeing at the moment is
tantamount to a kind of dysfunctional
relationship between men and women
playing out on the wider cultural stage
what does a healthy relationship look
like kind of linked to what we've been
discussing recently around the shadow I
think along with that question is what
is the shadow of masculinity but then
also less discussed what is the shadow
of femininity and I was thinking about
this but before I think about this a lot
actually because the shadow of the
masculine that that was the me to
movement as well was kind of showing up
the shadow of the masculine which is
obviously something that needs to happen
the shadow of the feminine is harder to
pin down I think
if you look at it in if you were to take
it just as a thought experiment in kind
of Taoist terms and you had each
opposite implies the other but there
really have to be opposite so if you see
and they would in kind of Chinese towers
and they see the masculine is obvious
and it's bright and it's right there
so the masculine shadow would be the
same it's so clear it's domination it's
controlled it's it's sort of its
aggressive it's all these things that
are quite easy to look at and easy to
define absolutely so by by that then the
shadow of the feminine should
automatically be shrouded mysterious
complex and I think that is one of the
powerful things about the red pill in
the whole phenomena of red pilling is
that it lifts a veil on AHA Wade this
there's a sense with the red pill I
think that a lot of people have watching
it I certainly did where I had a sense
of were the very water the very cultural
water I was swimming in is not what they
appear to be I think it I want to
interject here because we're two men
talking about the female shadow what I
want to say and what I think is really
interesting about the content we've got
coming up because we've got there was a
film done by a friend of ours Hannah who
did this film called from women to men
all about the female shadow and we've
got a long interview with her and a long
interview with a couple of the other
women who appeared in that film about
the female shadow and about their
ownership of of the ways they've acted
out and I think what's interesting as
well now is that there is a cultural as
I said we're about a year after me too
and I think the cultural conversation is
now at this point of recognizing we had
me to this kind of essential voicing of
a lot of suppressed anger or a lot of
suppress a lot of boundary setting by
women saying no this is not acceptable
behavior and where we are now especially
with Asia Argento one of the prime
movers of the me to movement has the
has turned out to be it looks a sexual
predator herself who'd paid off an
underaged guy that she'd slept with and
there was a really interesting article
quite recently by Barry Weiss in the New
York Times where she said this shows
that women are human too which is
basically what a lot of people have
wanted to hear it's like this this very
simplistic dynamic of women as only
victims and men as only perpetrators is
such a one-sided dynamic and now the
cultural conversation seems to have
swung to to this this place where we are
hopefully allowed to say men have a dark
side women have a dark side and it can
now be a more balanced conversation and
that's what I think really exciting
about the content we're putting out
because I think we're asking that
question and we're also asking
especially in the response to the red
pill like there's one thing as the film
and the the other thing is the cultural
response to the film and the incredibly
harsh reception that it got from a lot
of media platforms especially millennial
platforms like Vox and Vice I mean the
red pill is a very controversial film
and there were quite a few things said
about it and it was when we were in
America interviewing Warren Farrell and
he happens to be a neighbor of Cassie J
the the woman who made it and Cassie J
still describes herself as a liberal she
was a feminist when she went into making
the film and I I had a bit of a
suspicion as a filmmaker watching it it
just seemed so convenient that a
self-described feminist would go inside
the men's rights movement and have her
mind changed by what she found and I
have to say I was a little bit
suspicious about that I was a little bit
suspicious about how how it was a
perfect narrative and speaking to Warren
and this was unprompted I wasn't kind of
we weren't interrogating him about
Kathy's journey or anything like that he
just volunteered that Cassie had come to
him and said I went in I wanted to do
something we were an expose on the men's
rights activists
and even when she interviewed them she
had in the back of her mind a lot of
feminist talking points and a lot of
arguments without the way of saying and
it wasn't until she started watching the
the rushes back watching the the the
film back the footage to make the
documentary that she started listening
more to what they were saying and
understanding what they were saying and
came out with an appreciation of wow
there are some men's stories that are
not being heard there are some struggles
that men are having that are not being
heard and are not part of the
conversation and so she like I have
pretty much 100% certainty that her
journey was genuine and this was a
subtext of an awful lot of the the
coverage that the the need that sort of
negative coverage of the red pill was
people saying well just insinuating it
wasn't genuine that it was somehow it
was funded by men's rights activists and
it was a it was a Trojan horse done by
men's rights activists and I don't
believe that I think it was a genuine
film I think it was a genuine journey
and the irony is under a different in a
different circumstance she might be
looked on as a as a real feminist hero
she's a very successful documentary
filmmaker I think with a lot of bravery
as well she she talks about she did
actually lose some some friends when she
made the film and she I saw recently
she's even been outed or by the Prophet
the Southern Poverty Law Center which is
a kind of anti extremist organization in
America which seems to be an extremist
organization itself it had to backtrack
it it outed magical or Nawaz recently as
an extremist and he is an anti extremist
former Islamist that's really
fascinating what can be said in the cult
from what can't be said in the culture
and the fact that a documentary like the
red pill which along along with the
men's rights activists in it also had a
lot of feminist scholars in it as well
and you don't have to kind of agree with
everything the men's rights activists
are saying in it but in terms of a film
that adds an interesting perspective I
think it's definite
it definitely is that that film because
why it was really interesting to talk to
Cassie yeah just to back to your point
about what you said that if I'm not
really interesting in a different
setting
she might be held as a feminist hero I
think that's true and I'm just trying to
imagine what that setting might be it
certainly it certainly seems kind of
impossible now with the way feminism has
moved at least because it's much more
around it is in extra pick inextricably
tied to the same postmodern ideologies
that a lot of activism is tied to a lot
of critical theory is kind of an
academia is linked up in with the
oppressor oppressed again a name just
came up we were talking another very
successful woman Clare layman and
created the magazine quill let out of
her kitchen and it's now one of the sort
of most the biggest media success
stories of the last couple of years but
because quill let is very deliberately
anti identity politics and an to the
social justice left she is attacked on
Twitter rather than celebrated as a as a
successful woman the fact that it
doesn't really matter even if you the
ideology Trump's the personal story
pretty much all the time with the
identity politics left mmm yeah it does
and it's it's also it's an impossible
bind and it's also an interesting it
it's an interesting indication the
reaction to Clayman and Cassie J it for
me really points this weirdness that we
live in where the the identity politics
left in particular has kind of the
reigns of what's culturally acceptable
and a lot of pop culture power and a lot
of media power so they cannot even
though they can act as the oppressor
they can never admit that their acting
is the oppressor because the entire
worldview is based and there's only
oppressor and oppressed and so when they
are always on the side of the underdog
yeah and so this makes it impossible for
them to look inward of themselves and
realize that they now have the power or
a lot of power
more than perhaps they realize or maybe
not realize but want to realize and
they're not using it responsibly and
this is this the story of the last few
years for me I think if you see it
echoed everywhere and you see it echoed
in the gender discussion as well I think
so let's just hear a quick clip from
that interview with Cassie I know that
it helps a lot of people making this
film and and but I don't think it's I
don't think we're anywhere near where we
need to be and I think the red pill
movie was just a very early kind of
icebreaker into these conversations but
I think we have a long way to go with
gender relations and and hopefully
eventually finding a healthier
relationship between the genders and the
other interview that we're really
excited about putting out is with Warren
Farrell and we've talked before about
how if you see culture as a kind of
fractal pattern then the the fractal
pattern or the patterns that we saw
during the late 60s are still here but
they've just got bigger and the the
gender dynamics that first erupted in
the 60s the rise of women's liberation
and feminism and this this now to me
feels like we're in the same dynamic but
we look back and we kind of looked
through the wrong end of the telescope
we assumed that everyone back in the 60s
was part of this movement but the fact
that it that we know about it shows that
it wasn't universal it was it was an
outlier it was a new thing it was we
were always attuned to the new and what
some interesting about Warren Farrell is
that he has been living this dynamic
this same dynamic since the 60s a
fascinating individual story because he
was one of the very first male feminists
he was part of the he was on the board
of the National Organization for Women
in America and he he then at the same
time started leading men's groups and in
the men's groups he was hearing stories
that he realized were not part of the
conversation and when he started
bringing the experience of the way that
men have been hurt and the way that men
feel that they have to perform certain
gender roles and that they are seen as
success he uses the words for example
that yes women
women are often objectified and seen as
sex objects and judged by their looks
men feel that they're often judged by
success he calls success objects they're
judged by their ability to provide
they're judged by their wealth they're
judged by their status there was a
beautiful moment I really I know that we
both really enjoyed meeting him and
spending time with him there's a really
beautiful moment towards the end of the
interview where he said men have makeup
to male makeup is I am dr. Warren
Farrell best-selling author of the boy
crisis and what's my makeup I'm doctor
best-selling author
that's all makeup it's me being afraid
of saying I'm also Warren Farrell
vulnerable human being in these five or
six ways considering he's often framed
as the father of the men's movement and
the men's movement especially in America
has a really bad reputation and perhaps
quite rightly I mean I asked him that in
the interview whether he agreed that
some of the bad press at the men's
movement had was deserved and he agreed
that it was and I think certainly a lot
of the tactics that I see from some of
the more extreme men's rights activists
in America I can see why they have a bad
reputation and it's not I don't think
it's doing they're there cause any good
they they kind of turn into the thing
that they're supposedly fighting against
but as I said at the beginning Warren
Farrell is someone who's very much
focused on what the healthy
relationships look like what are the
things that need to be expressed from
men and from women so that we can have
healthy relationships and if we have a
culture where men are on one hand
encouraged to express their feelings but
also on the other hand often the culture
will describe it as whining when then do
express their feelings there's a kind of
double bind and a lot of men feel stuck
in that in the moment yeah what really
struck me about Warren Farrell aside
from him is an individual that I found
it's very authentic is his his focus in
in the myth of male power his first kind
of best selling
book it's very nuanced and it's really a
balanced perspective of going into the
economics and that also dictated the
relationship structures we had for a
very long time
and pointing out that it's not as simple
as just saying men were patriarchs and
they held women down and just because
you know because they're dysfunctional
in some way it was it was a lot more
complex than that and yes some of that
went on of course but it was also a case
of men had to go out and be the
breadwinners men were expendable as well
and then we shifted in the 60s and maybe
slightly before to different kind of
relationship for the first time ever
happening so this is all very new the
dynamics are experiencing all really
fresh like yeah and so and now we said
in the interview really nice thing which
was around like we're not designed to be
functional
we're design in terms of like
relationships how we relate to each
other's men and women like which is time
to be dysfunctional
we're designed to survive basically what
he says and that you know so we have he
says we have an opportunity now where we
have a lot more equality to figure out
how do we how the hell do we get on with
each other in a in a way that is
conducive to our health and our
children's health as well and I found
that was the overriding message I got
from him I think is in his work as well
is it's really about I find that really
useful framing that globally and I think
we might have talked about this before
what we're seeing is the result of an
incredibly dysfunctional relationship
it's like the gender dynamics we're
seeing on the macro scale feel like the
micro scale would be like two parents
having a massive argument more like two
teenagers having a massive argument I
think there's a second part to that
interview with Warren Farrell which is
going to be a patreon exclusive so if
you want to see that become a patron I
hope that we are now at a stage where
all sides of that debate can be heard
because the eruption of Me 2 which was
October last year it were it was said
quite explicitly at times men now is now
is not your time to speak and I can
understand that because these are a lot
of the time or voices that have
heard for a long time and but that it
cannot remain that cannot remain as a
dynamic by definition a relationship has
to be both sides speaking and I think a
healthy relationship is where both sides
are allowed to speak and I think a
healthy cultural dynamic is when
something like the red pill is made it
is not immediately shut down is it not
immediately criticized as I think vice
called it you men's men's rights
bullshit documentary another thing just
came up for me that that he said
relating to the kind of that I guess
necessary outburst that happens after me
to was you know procedure therapist who
said obviously the longer someone's held
something in the more it comes the more
anger is behind it when it finally comes
out and now I think was that was very
evident there and that makes sense
and I wonder now I see that anger as
well in the men's rights movement as
well and I understand why it's there too
I do
but the what the next stage looks like
for me is a kind of a meeting where the
anger has extinguished itself somewhat
and maybe we're getting to that point
but where the conversation comes it's a
conversation about responsibility I
think ultimately it's a conversation on
both sides around what does it mean to
be responsible for yourself and your
actions as a human being
whether you're a man or woman that's
what you do in couple you know in
couples counseling you talk from the eye
you talk about yourself you talk about
you don't you know actually again Warren
made a really good point where he said
having a dynamic like feminism has at
the moment where everything is men's
fault I'm being broad with families and
I'm talking about maybe the the worst
sides of it where everything is men's
fault
he equates it to a man going to a
psychiatrist and sitting down I mean
like right okay well I'm here but what
you need to know is that everything is
my wife's fault
the reason I'm Peter is because of her
and I've listed out 14 points around
where she's a total fuck out and I'm
gonna list them out to you and you
better agree with me otherwise I'm gonna
stop
the therapist selection and a similar
impossible dynamic where nothing can
happen that I still feel is what we're
kind of largely in and that's why people
are allowed to talk at university that's
why Cassie is still as of like today
getting slammed in the press and why
there's just a lot of
mischaracterization all around the place
and I think something has to give some
kind of humility or humanity has to give
in order for that conversation start
happening and on that point it might be
a good time to talk about Hannah's film
yeah so this is one of the most
interesting and it's a sort of
experimental thing that we've done Hanna
produced this film which has gone pretty
viral on online called from women to men
I am a woman
[Music]
who has been hurt by men I'm a woman who
has hurt men who has hurt men and she's
a she's a conflict negotiator that's
what she did for many years in some of
the world so the most intractable
conflict and the thing that she realized
is that we cannot move forward until you
own our part of whatever dynamic we
can't move forward in any in any
conflict until we own our side and we
own the stuff that we've done and she
then went through a process of sending
this poem out to many other women and
they then came together to make the film
and a lot of them would then choose the
bits of the poem that really spoke to
them the things that they'd done in the
past and a lot of them said they went
through a real process through doing it
as well there's a really controversial
piece it's it had really polarized
reaction online but it's had about a
million views altogether and I've seen a
lot of especially men from some of the
the men's groups that I've seen online
very touched by it a lot of people said
it brought them to tears I do mean over
time when we all take responsibility for
the part each of us plays in this battle
when we can truly empower ourselves by
owning our parts of the mess and bring
an end to the cycle of hurting and
blaming I begin today I begin today I
begin today I begin today you got a
couple of films off the back of that one
of which is an interview with Hannah and
a couple of the other women who appeared
in the film asking why why they've got
involved in the project in the first
place what they got from it and what the
reaction was whether they have any
regrets and another film which is
slightly more experimental which is and
as Hannah said in her in her film what
she wanted was to start a new kind of
conversation between women women and men
and so we try and model that with Hannah
her friend Elaine who appears in the
film myself and Rath
who is a facilitator a therapist who's
been working for about 40 years with
these issues the male and the female so
basically this is an attempt to model
this kind of conversation what does a
healthy conversation between men and
women look like which involves us taking
ownership of our staff and then meeting
from a place of real ownership and real
communication and we'll see if that
works yeah well hopefully it kind of has
to work I think at some point globally
that kind of conversation has to be the
norm and in fact again to bring it back
to Warren Farrell opus it was a long
interview and he said lots of
interesting things they're doing it in
Denmark they're having their teaching
children these types of conversation and
that seems the natural thing is that
this is a skill that people need to have
is to be able to and I think personal
responsibility is the beginning of it
and I think what's really powerful about
Hannah's film or just powerful about
just the idea of that kind of
conversation is that it starts with
personal responsibility and that's where
that seems to be what the culture is
crying out for at the moment is this
kind of a reconnection to personal
responsibility and a movement away from
everything's about being oppressed or
being an oppressor and either being a
victim or a perpetrator it's the yeah it
seems to me like it that conversation
can't really happen within that the
environment within an environment based
on a press or oppressed I think that
just has to go like the broken green
we've called it it had it's not a place
for that conversation to happen that
conversation needs to happen in some
kind of new less ideological or post
ideological space which hopefully is
rising up somewhere or in the ether
somewhere at the moment yeah I also want
to say about Hannah's Vil that I've had
very different reactions to it at
different times when I first heard it
when she delivered it as a poem in a
therapeutic training I was really
touched and it was it was a really
powerful ownership and then when I've
seen it since and I've seen the film
sometimes I watched it and I just
thought wow this is just it's so
countercultural it almost feels too much
because on its own it does feel
balance it's like well okay but that's
kind of the point is that it's almost
like a little bomb in that inside that
ideology because it's so anti the
narrative that we live with all the time
for women to pretty much just own their
their stuff without any kind of context
or balancing of men owning their stuff
at the same time so it feels you know
what
on its own it feels slightly unbalanced
but I guess that's the essence of great
art in a way great art is not meant to
make you feel comfortable it's mostly
supposed to make you feel uncomfortable
and even I have felt uncomfortable
watching that film every now and again
and yeah I hope that in the recording
that we've put together with raffia
there's a certain balance in terms of us
owning our stuff and then building more
of a complete conversation around it as
well as you were as you're describing
that that I know that feeling I call it
like vicarious discomfort it's like a
sense of how something will land in the
culture and I feel like some part of me
which of course were tribal pea beings
now even if even there's a lot within
the culture below I disagree with I
still feel that twins I've again had a
similar experience watching Hannah's
film I think the first time it was
incredibly emotional you know it's a
real - really but a real heartfelt
feeling of like relief of like wow okay
that feels really just very loving and
very responsible like really a really
powerful loving feminine energy that it
comes with that but also that feeling of
like wow this is gonna be dynamite
remember that was the that was what I
thought first time so I was like wow
this is gonna this is definitely gonna
ruffle some feathers which it has yes
yeah but again feather ruffling is is
the point of art I think the point of
good art and that's what leads to yeah
growth I think it's worth also saying
that our interest in these subjects it
probably comes from our own histories in
terms of a lot of the the kind of the
inner work that we've done around
masculinity we both teach men's work and
ultimately these questions can only be
resolved really an embodied
it it cannot just become a conversation
about masculinity and femininity because
then you get into this kind of swampy
relativistic suit of or what do you mean
by masculine what do you mean by
feminine surely we're just humans and
then it it all starts to kind of become
very relativistic very quickly whereas I
know that my experience of doing work or
a really connect with myself in my
masculine that there's a real embodied
presence that I can bring to these
questions and then a lot of these kind
of gender dynamics resolve themselves
very very quickly and if you're watching
this new you're interested in this
subject we are teaching we've got a
men's workshop coming up in November
we've got a women's workshop coming up
in September at the end of September
that is being taught by some amazing
facilitators including Hannah actually
who did the film and we've got a
polarity workshop coming up in January
as well I think it's so important to tie
this this content the ideas together
with the embodied work because otherwise
if we just stay up in the heads we just
stay up in the conceptual realm and then
nothing gets resolved I think it's also
important to add none of the workshops
about telling anyone what masculinity or
femininity is it's really because you
can't you each individual has to connect
to what that is experientially within
themselves and a space like that it's
it's a flow state it's getting into a
flow state and in a flow state the
concepts the ideas they are of like
they're not important at all in a sense
it's the experience and so experience
again is also what really like meeting
human to human and communicating human
to human that's also absolutely key in
developing our own ideas but then also
developing ideas collectively and on
that now we also have another event
coming up which is join the great
intellectual awakening and that's going
to be on the 18th of September in London
we'll put
notes down in the show notes with a link
to it but again that event it's not just
us talking about what's that's run it
this is pretty much us trying to create
that we've always wanted to create a
community around these ideas and this is
our first event to try and create that
kind of community so we're gonna talk
about rebel wisdoms were gonna talk
about a history and show some of the
clips from some of the films and then
trying to create some kind of way of
having having these kind of generative
dialogues which we've talked about
before what does it mean to have a
dialogue where you go in genuinely
trying from a place of not knowing and
inquiring and and finding the answers
for yourselves rather than this kind of
very ideological way of trying to kind
of persuade someone that you're right
yeah or what Jordan Greene whole talk
about like the old broadcast model or
something you know T we cultural be
broadcast to you an idea through
broadcast to you and we live in a
different paradigm now which is the more
decentralized kind of knowledge sharing
18th of September if you're in London
come along to the great intellectual
awakening and one other thing we've got
we've recently put up a few pieces on
patreon for patrons only
we've got another amazing piece with Tim
lot who we had an interview with
recently talking about the links between
Jordan Peterson and Alan Watts and
Jordan Pederson has often been described
as doing for Western philosophy and
Western spirituality what Alan Watts did
for Eastern spirituality back in the 50s
and 60s and there's really interesting
parallels between the two and really
interesting differences between the two
as well and Tim lot who was the first
guy to write a profile of Jordan
Peterson for The Spectator magazine in
look yeah last year also is an expert on
Alan Watts so we had a really
interesting dialogue with Tim and that's
we're gonna put that live on patreon in
the next few days so if you're
interested in that or you want to see
the second part of the Warren Farrell
interview then become a patron
thanks for watching and see you next
time